Mss.B.W564
American Philosophical Society
- XIA. Audio/visual, 1910-2003 (Box 255-262)
  - 4. Cassettes, floppy discs, CD-ROM, 1966-1997 (Box 261-262)
    - Place of Man in Cosmology, 1969; Rec. 214; 1.0 Tape(s)
      November 11, 1969. Leon Lecture at the University of Pennsylvania
    - Dr. Reines, Nov. 20, 1969; Rec. 213; 2.0 Reel(s)
      November 20, 1969. Recording of a seminar held at University of California, Irvine in which Frederick Reines participated. Wheeler did not take part in the seminar. 7" reels of audiotape
    - Earth, Solar System, Cosmos: Current Problems of Cosmology, 1969; Rec. 215; 1.0 Tape(s)
      December 1969. Symposium or panel discussion at the 136th meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Boston, Massachusetts. Wheeler was a participant
    - Beyond the End of Time, 1973; Rec. 205; 1.0 Reel(s)
      January 18, 1973. An address given as part of the "Distinguished Lecture Series" (no. 1) at IBM, Yorktown Heights, New York. Includes two abstracts which have been photocopied and processed into Series IVA, "Beyond the End of Time." 7" reel of audiotape.
    - Copernicus Symposium, 1973; Rec. 206; 1.0 Reel(s)
      April 25, 1973. National Academy of Sciences annual meeting. 7" reel of audiotape
    - International Symposium on the Chemistry and Physics of Fission, 1973; Rec. 207; 1.0 Reel(s)
      August 16, 1973. 7" reel of audiotape
    - Birth and Death of a Star, 1973; 1.0 Film reel(s)
      Motion picture for Los Angeles Public TV. Directed by Mr. Shapiro. Intermediary -- Don McCormick, American Institute of Physics. 12" reel of film.
    - In Search of Infinity, 1973; Rec. 216; 1.0 Tape(s)
      Planetarium show from the Manitoba Museum of Man and Nature. Includes 90 seconds of an interview with Wheeler regarding black holes, superspace, etc.
    - [Untitled cassette tape], [1973]; Rec. 226; 1.0 Tape(s)
      Address given by Wheeler concerning black holes at a symposium celebrating the 500th anniversary of the birth of Copernicus. Following Wheeler's presentation is a question and answer session, and further discussion by other physicists.
    - Is Cosmogony a Part of Physics?, 1975; Rec. 208; 1.0 Reel(s)
      February 24, 1975. Seattle, Washington. Includes discussion. 7" reel of audiotape
    - How Did the Universe Come into Being: Forever Beyond Exploration?, 1975-1976; 3.0 Item(s)
      - Syracuse, New York Recording, 1975; Rec. 209; 1.0 Reel(s)
        March 21, 1975. 7" reel of audiotape
      - Syracuse, New York Recording, 1975; Rec. 217; 1.0 Tape(s)
        March 21, 1975. Audiocasette tape version
      - Gainesville, Florida Recording, 1976; Rec. 223; 1.0 Tape(s)
        January 28, 1976
    - Interview by Science Correspondent Alan Hammond, 1975; Rec. 210; 1.0 Reel(s)
      Regarding the Hydrogen Bomb. Interview held at 30 Maxwell Lane, Princeton, New Jersey. November 28, 1975. 7" reel of audiotape
    - Future of Physics, 1976; Rec. 212; 1.0 Reel(s)
      April 26, 1976. Address given before the National Academy of Sciences annual meeting. 7" reel of audiotape
    - Minneapolis Discussion, 1977; 2.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      Tapes 10-11. May 21, 1977
    - Black Hole and Beyond, 1977; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      Nuclear science symposium, June 6, 1977
    - Tape 1 and Tape 2, 1977; 2 Microcassettes (Box 261)
      Dictation tapes dated November 21, 1977
    - [Lecture], Wheeler, 1978; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      November 13, 1978
    - History of my Interest in Good Nutritional Health and Degenerative Disease, Pritikin, 1978, 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      Nathan Pritikin, Longevity Center, Santa Monica, CA
    - Lipotoxemia: Nutrition as Related to Degenerative Disease, 1978; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
    - Interview for Oral History Project, 1979; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      University of Texas. Interview by T. F. Castillo. April 6, 1979
    - Einstein and the Mystery of the Quantum, 1979; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      American Chemical Society Speech, at the National Academy of Science. September 11, 1979
    - Role of Consciousness, 1979; 3.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      American Association for the Advancement of Science. 79T-4891, 79T-4892, 79T-4893
    - E. S. P. Series, Harvey Black, 1980; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      Aired on Wisconsin Public Radio, February 25-29, 1980
    - Physics 341, 1980; 2.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      March 20-23, 1980
    - Reality, Illusion, and Time, 1980; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      NYU # I. November 13, 1980
    - Time and Light, 1980; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      NYU # II. November 14, 1980
    - Beyond the End of Time, 1980; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      NYU # III. November 17, 1980
    - Continuing Search. 3rd Annual Vanuxem Lecture, 1981; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      Princeton, March 19, 1981
    - Elementary Quantum Phenomenon as Building Unit, 1981; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      4th lecture at the Rhotenberg [sic] Conference, August 16-29, 1981
    - Nobel [Conference], Wheeler Address, 1981; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      Gustavus Aldolphus College, October 6-7, 1981
    - Sakharov Conference, John Wheeler, 1981; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
    - Mills Lecture, 1982; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      March 24, 1982
    - Kepler Lecture, 1982; 2 Microcassettes (Box 261)
      May 7, 1982
    - Science in the U.S. in the 20th Century, 1983; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      April 15, 1983
    - One Man and his Universe, 1983; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      BBC, Newcastle-upon-Tyne interview, May 1983
    - Ghost in the Atom, 1983; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      BBC, with Paul Davies, at Newcastle-upon-Tyne. November 15, 1983
    - Risk of Nuclear Energy, 1984; Rec. 218; 1.0 Tape(s)
      February 26, 1984. Includes Salado Lecture, Questions and Answers
    - Greats Lecture, 1984; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      April 12, 1984
    - Art of Science, 1984; Rec. 221; 1.0 Tape(s)
      May 1, 1984. Interview with Robert Arnold for the Voice of America
    - On the Why of the Quantum, 1984; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 261)
      NATO Advanced Study Institute, St. John's College, Santa Fe, New Mexico, June 6, 1984
    - William Bolling's thoughts and questions on physics (pair creation, s-matrix, b-matrix, Einstein) and socio-political interests, 1984; Rec. 225; 2.0 Tape(s)
    - Interview with Jan Stanley-Muchow, 1985; Rec. 222; 2.0 Tape(s)
      May 14-15, 1985
    - Conversation with Frank Williamson, Jr., regarding John Mauchly, 1985; Rec. 224; 1.0 Tape(s)
      [December 29, 1985]
    - Inside Soviet Science: Promise and Peril, 1986; Rec. 219; 1.0 Tape(s)
      March 26, 1986. Compton Memorial Lecture, Washington University
    - Elan and Morale in Science, 1988; Rec. 137; 2.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      John Clarke Slater Symposium. The Grand Enterprise: Modern Physical Science in America, 1920-1960. Talk given at the American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia, March 18, 1988. Two copies (Rec. 137 & Box 262).
    - Interview with Professor John Wheeler, 1988; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      6UVS FM, 92.1: The Sound Alternative. Perth, West Australia. Interview by Virginia Rivalland. Broadcast August 8, 1988
    - Gravity: What is its role in the scheme of existence?, 1988; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Views of the Universe, Octagon Lectures, Professor John Wheeler. Australia, August 9, 1988
    - Fission, L. A. / Putnam Waldron, 1988; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Side A: Fission L. A., September 1988; Side B: Putnam Waldron, October 14, 1988
    - Sanyo Answering Machine, 1990; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      September 1990
    - Quantum Mechanics: New Age Loophole or Support for Creation, 1990; 2.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Dr. Hugh Ross, ReasonS To Believe, Pasadena, CA
    - Black Holes, Past, Present, Future, 1990; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Chapman Lecture. University of Alaska-Fairbanks, September 13, 1990
    - Niels Bohr Lecture, 1991; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Lecture given to Physics 453 Class, University of Texas at Austin. Only final half recorded. December 6, 1991
    - Spain Lecture, 1992; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      J. A. Wheeler and B. Schumacher. Transcribed January 1992
    - How to Build a Reactor, 1992; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      APS/AAPT, April 23, 1992
    - Black Hole, 25 Years Later, 1994; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Santigo CECS Congress
    - Wheeler, 1994; 1 Microcassette (Box 262)
      May 15, 1994
    - Black Holes and Beyond, 1997; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Sides 3-4 only, questions. February 26, 1997
    - Fields Medallists' Lectures, 1999; 1 CD-ROM; Atiyah, Michael Francis, 1929-; Iagolnitzer, Daniel (Box 262)
      PDF copy stored on a CD-ROM disk
    - Edward Teller Commemoration, 2003; 1 DVD (Box 262)
      November 3, 2003
    - After Dinner Speaker, n.d.; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
    - Interview with Takashi Watanabe, n.d.; Rec. 220; 1.0 Tape(s)
      NHK - Nippon Hoso Kyokai Tape
    - Faculty House, n.d.; 2.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
      Second tape merely labeled "Tape 2A"
    - Fink trans. of my delayed choice, n.d.; 1 Microcassette (Box 262)
    - Ne'eman, n.d.; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
    - Oklahoma City, n.d.; 1.0 Tape(s) (Box 262)
- XIIA. Collected Works, 1929-1987; 12.0 Volume(s) (Volume 114-125)
  Reprints written by Wheeler from 1929-1987, bound together in to a twelve volume set.
  - Collected Papers, 1929-1947, 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 114)
  - Collected Papers. Reprints to 1954, 1936-1954; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 115)
  - Collected Papers. Reprints to 1960, 1946-1960; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 116)
  - Collected Papers. Reprints to 1965, 1961-1965; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 117)
  - Collected Works to 1967, 1942-1967; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 118)
  - Collected Works to 1970, 1968-1970; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 119)
  - Reprints. September 1971- September 1972, 1969-1972; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 120)
    Relativity Group Under J. A. Wheeler. NSF Grant GP30799X
  - Collected Works to 1973, 1947-1973; 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 121)
  - Collected Works, 1974-1978, 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 122)
  - Collected Works, 1978-1981, 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 123)
    See also Series IV: "Typescripts" and "Speeches and Interviews" for the same period.
  - Collected Works, 1981-1984, 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 124)
  - Collected Works, 1984-1987, 1.0 Volume(s); Wheeler, John Archibald, 1911-2008 (Volume 125)
- XIIIA. Realia, 1942-2005 (Box 263-266)
  An assortment of objects--drafting tools, a rolodex collection, pins, souvenirs, and commemorative and award medals. Of interest are two small pieces of graphite from the first nuclear reactor and numerous award medals won by Wheeler, including the National Medal of Science and the Wolf Prize Pin. Materials in Series XIIIA were accessioned in 1994 and later years.
  - Drafting Tools, n.d. (Box 263)
  - Open card files, n.d. (Box 264)
    Address book consisting of two rolodex files of contacts.
  - Pins, souvenirs, etc., 1942-2001 (Box 265)
    - APS Fellow Pin, n.d. (Box 265)
    - APS 100 Years, A Century of Physics Pin, 1999 (Box 265)
    - B Reactor. Hanford, WA. Buttons, n.d.; 2.0 Item(s) (Box 265)
    - BCC 1989. Pin (Box 265)
    - Bomb Damage Effect Computer, 1964 (Box 265)
    - Engraved Name Plate, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Euro Tunnel Rock, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Fudan University Pin, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Graphite from CP-1, First Nuclear Reactor, December 2, 1942, Stagg Field -- The University of Chicago (Box 265)
    - Graphite Used in the First Atomic Pile, 1942 (Box 265)
      In Which Man (Dr. Enrico Fermi), for the First Time, Attained and Controlled a Nuclear Chain Reaction on December 2, 1942. Gift from Lt. Col. William Sapper, 1985.
    - High Island Logo (Box 265)
      Taken from "Mixed Collection" folder.
    - [High Island Logo] (Box 265)
      Stamp mold
    - IUPAP Name Tag, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Peking University Pin, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Princeton University. 1746 Society Pin, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Siegel d. Uni Koln. Wax Seal, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Unidentified Embedded Plant Specimen, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Unidentified Pins, n.d.; 6.0 Item(s) (Box 265)
    - Unidentified Stone, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Universidad Politecnica Madrid. Instituto de Fusion Nuclear. Plate, n.d. (Box 265)
    - Wolf Prize Pin, 1997 (Box 265)
  - Medals, 1946-1991, n.d. (Box 266)
    Boxed in a small wooden box adorned with Chinese script
    - Albert Abraham Michelson, 1852-1931, 1973 (Box 266)
      Hall of Fame for Great Americans at New York University
    - Albert Einstein, 1879-1955, 1979 (Box 266)
      Jerusalem Centennial Symposium, March 1979
    - Albert Einstein Commemorative Coins, 1979; 2.0 Item(s) (Box 266)
      Two commemorative five-franc coins issued by Switzerland
    - Albert Einstein Society Award, 1988 (Box 266)
      Inscription on medal reads: "Verliehen durch die Albert Einstein-Gesellschaft in Anerkennung der hohen Verdienste an Bern. John Archibald Wheeler, 6.6.1988"
    - Battelle -- Halfway Thru Our First Century, 1979 (Box 266)
      Paper weight
    - First International A. D. Sakharov Conference on Physics, 1991 (Box 266)
      P. N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Moscow, May 1991
    - Gordon Battelle, 1883-1923, 1983 (Box 266)
      Battelle Memorial Institute, Science in the Service of Mankind
    - Hans Christian Oersted, Teacher, Scientist, 1820, 1983 (Box 266)
      American Association of Physics Teachers. For Notable Contributions to the Teaching of Physics. Awarded to John Archibald Wheeler
    - Institute for Advanced Study, Einstein Centennial, 1879-1979 (Box 266)
    - J. Robert Oppenheimer Memorial Prize, 1984 (Box 266)
      Center for Theoretical Studies, University of Miami. John A. Wheeler, November 27, 1984
    - James Smithson, 1765-1829, 1965 (Box 266)
      Presented at the bicentennial of James Smithson, 1765-1965
    - Johns Hopkins University, Fifty Year Alumnus, 1981 (Box 266)
      John A. Wheeler, 1931
    - Karl Herzfeld Science Medal, 1972 (Box 266)
      Catholic University of America
    - Maria Sklodowska Curie, 1867-1967 (Box 266)
      Wielkiej Uczonej. Stulecie Urodzin ("Great Scholar. Centennial Birthday")
    - Max Planck, 1858-1958 (Box 266)
      Deutsche Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin
    - Monie A. Ferst Award, 1981 (Box 266)
      Sigma XI. In recognition of outstanding contributions to research through education. John A. Wheeler, 1981
    - Mikolaj Kopernik, 1473-1973 (Box 266)
    - National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, Founded 1863, 1963 (Box 266)
      National Academy of Sciences Centennial, 1963
    - National Medal of Science, 1970 (Box 266)
      Awarded by the President of the United States of America to John A. Wheeler, 1970
    - Princeton University, Bicentennial, 1746-1946, 2.0 Item(s) (Box 266)
    - Unidentified Medal, n.d. (Box 266)
      Unidentified medal with Chinese writing.
    - Universitas Carolina Pragensis, n.d. (Box 266)
      Facultas Mathematica Physicaque